Guide to the Howard R. Lamar Center for the Study of Frontiers and Borders, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Howard R. Lamar Center for the Study of Frontiers and Borders, Yale University, records
2000-2012
RU 1117
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.83
(5 boxes)
The records of the Howard R. Lamar Center consist of materials related to Lamar Research Fellows and scholarship recipents, as well as scheduled lectures and other events hosted by the Howard R. Lamar Center.
Yale University. Howard R. Lamar Center for the Study of Frontiers and Borders
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from the Howard R. Lamar Center in 2012.
General
Forms part of Yale Record Group 37 (YRG 37), Records of associations, institutes, centers, and organizations affiliated with Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The records of the Howard R. Lamar Center consist of materials related to Lamar Research Fellows and scholarship recipents, as well as scheduled lectures and other events hosted by the Howard R. Lamar Center.
Biographical / Historical
The Howard R. Lamar Center for the Study of Frontiers and Borders at Yale University was established to further the advanced historical study of North American frontiers and borders, as well as the comparative study of the frontier experience throughout the world.
The Center honors Howard Roberts Lamar, Sterling Professor Emeritus of History and former President of the University. Lamar, well-known for his pivotal contributions to the field of western history, continues to work as a scholar and adviser. His The New Encyclopedia of the American West (Yale University Press) was described by historian Stephen E. Ambrose as "a monumental achievement in the historiography of the American West. Howard Lamar had rendered our nation a great service by compiling this magisterial and indispensable reference volume."
The Center's principal priority is the support of graduate study in the departments of History and American Studies at Yale University by providing grants for dissertation research on topics relating to the Center's scholarly interests, by sponsoring talks and workshops by scholars, and in keeping with Howard Lamar's dedication and generosity of spirit as a teacher, mentor, and friend to generations of Yale students, by seeking to create at Yale a community of mutually-supportive scholars interested in frontiers and borders.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Conditions Governing Access
The records for the Howard R. Lamar Center are restricted until January 1, 2087, as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Graduate Students -- Scholarships, Fellowships, etc.; Research institutes; Scholarships; West (U.S.); Lamar, Howard Roberts, 1923-; Yale University -- Funds and scholarships; Yale University. American Studies Program
- Records concerning research fellows and scheduled events, 2000-2012; Accession 2013-A-005
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2087
  - Posters, 2000-2012 (Box 1)
  - Posters and announcements, 2000-2012 (Box 2)
  - Posters, brochures, postcards, announcements, 2000-2012 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lamar Research Fellows General 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - French Colonial Historical Society, May 2002 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lamar Research Fellows General 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Lamar Symposium September 2000 Opening Event and Robin Winks (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Betts Lecture November 2001 - Patty Limerick (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lamar Center Symposium September 2001-Ethnic Cleansing-Jay's [Gitlin] Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Lamar Center Symposium September 2001-Ethnic Cleansing-Lists and Invites (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Lamar Center Symposium September 2001-Ethnic Cleansing-Records (Box 3, Folder 24)
    General
    Folder not received.
  - Lamar Center Symposium September 2001-Ethnic Cleansing-Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Lamar Center Symposium September 2001-Ethnic Cleansing-Correspondence General (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Lamar Center Symposium September 2001-Ethnic Cleansing-More Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Lamar Center Symposium November-December 2001 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Lamar Center Events 01-02-Melody Webb, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Lamar Center Events 01-02-Robert Utley Lecture, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Lamar Center Events 01-02-Sheila McManus, Feb. 02, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Lamar Center Events 01-02-McLoud Film Screening, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Lamar Center Symposiums 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Lamar Center Symposiums 2002-2003-Jay's Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Lamar Center Events Betts Lecture November 2002-2003 - Jim Ronda (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Lamar Center Events 2002-2003-Zacharias Kunuk Screening- Atanarjuat: The Fast Runner (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Lamar Center Teas 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Solnit, Rebecca Talk 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Lamar Center Events-Talks 2002-2003, Michael Quinn, Mario DePillis (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Lamar Center Events-Talks 2002-2003 Lecture, Mark Brilliant, Feb. 2003 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Stiles, T.J., Talk November 2002, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Lamar Center Betts Lecture November 2003 - Elliott West (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Dissertation Workshop for Centers of Western History April 2009 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Lamar Center Flooding and other Problems 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Lamar Center at WHA and OAH 2004-2005-Tributes to Howard (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Betts Lecture, November 2004 - Dippie, Bryan (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Buffalo Roast with Sam Arnold, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - World Oil Frontiers Conference, Spring 2005, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Carson, Jamey April 2004 Lecture, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Lamar Center Symposium-Women and Colonization, Fall, 2003, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Lecture, Namaias, June, April 2004, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Lecture, Thompson, John, December 2003, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Lecture, Mitchell, Don, February, 2004, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Lamar Research Fellows 2004-2005,General (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Executive Committee Meeting 5-2001, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Lamar Scholars, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Rebecca Solnit, Lecture, March 26, 2003, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - T.J. Styles, Lecture, Nov. 20, 2002, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Toby McLeod, Lecture, Movie Screening, Feb. 11, 2002, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Mario DePillis/Michael Quinn, Talk, Feb. 26, 2003, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - June Namias, Talk, April 8, 2004, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Screening, Atanarjuat: The Fast Runner, Zack Kunuk, October 2002, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Meeting, John Cloud, October 19, 2004, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Pathways Conference American Indian Studies, April 23-25, 2004, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Sandweiss and Fabian Talks, Spring 2005, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Betts Lecture, Jim Ronda, November 8, 2002, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - John Mack Faragher Book Signing, Feb. 24, 2005, Book Haven, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Ethnic Cleansing Symposium, Fall, 2001, Jay's Notes and Correspondence, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Lamar Research Fellows-General, 2001-2012 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Clay Applicants, 2006-2008 (Box 5, Folder 117)